【负 重 前 行】
妈
Ma.
好棒
That's it.
妈妈
Mama.
凯伊？
Kay?
你们好啊
Hey!
- 安迪 - 你们好啊
- Andy - Hello!
（隔离救助包）
我们的粮食够吃三餐
So we have three meals.
最多能吃四餐
Four at a stretch.
知道了
Okay.
也就是说我们剩下四分之一的粮食
So that means we're down to quarter rations.
明白了
Okay.
有什么我不知情的计划你想让我知道吗？
Is there a plan I'm not aware of? Want to fill me in on it?
- 不 我喜欢你的计划 - 哪一个计划？
- No, I like your plan. - Which is?
吃笔的计划
That we eat the pens.
听着 这里有个小镇
Look, there's a town here.
距离这里不超过30或40公里
Can't be more than 30 or 40 km from where we are.
那是个农村 人不多
Right? It's rural. There's not a lot of people.
我们去弄台车 塞满补给 去看看那里有什么
I say we get a car, fill it with supplies, we just see what's out there.
- 我们已经看过外面的情况了 - 我们看到的是几周前的情况
- We've seen what's out there. - We've seen what's back there. Weeks ago.
- 那里岸边很安静... - 我们讨论过这事了
- It's quiet on the banks... - We talked about this.
- 要是我们能逃出去呢？- 要是逃不出去呢？
- What if we've outrun it? - What if we haven't?
我们必须要待在这里
Where we need to be, actually, is here.
这条河已经把我们带到这里
The river has got us this far.
若我们做了正确决定 就能抵达这里 所以我们必须做有把握的事
If we play it smart, it'll get us there, but we have to stick to what we know.
有把握的事？在我们发现这艘船前 你根本没上过船
What we know? You had barely set foot on a boat before we found this thing.
这船比我们的年龄加在一起还老
I mean, it's older than both of us put together.
要是引擎坏了呢？那会发生什么事？
What if the engine goes? What happens then?
我们还要考虑到萝西
We have to think about Rosie.
是吗？抱歉 我没想到 不然你以为我在搞什么？
Do we? I hadn't thought of that. What the fuck do you think I'm doing?
听着 上岸是我们最后的选择
Look, we can't set foot on the shore until it is our last and only option.
事情就是这样 我很抱歉
That's just the way it is, I'm sorry.
那会发生在我们女儿被饿死之前还是之后？
So is that going to be before or after our daughter starves to death?
嘘
Shh.
天啊
Jesus Christ.
我的天啊
My God.
天啊
Wow.
- 有鱼上钩吗？- 嗯 还没
- Any bites? - Um-mm. Not yet.
- 等一下 - 快点 用那个东西直接钩上来
- Oh, hang on a second. - Quick. Hook him with the thing.
- 什么东西？钩子吗？- 对 把它拉上来 快点
- What, with the hook? Whoa. - Yeah, bring him in, quick!
- 什么？- 这是什么？
- What? - What's that?
- 这是你从哪里弄来的？- 从那艘坏掉的游艇
- Where did you get this from? - From the wrecked yacht.
说谢谢就行了 看看这个
Say thank you. Look at this.
这至少够我们吃三个月了
There's enough there for three months, at least.
- 这是个好消息 小蓝 - 这是很棒的消息
- Hey, this is good news, Blue. - It's great news.
你不用担心 这不是什么难事
You're not worried. It was a one - man job.
进去 出来 简单又安全
In and out. Easy. Safe.
拜托 这是件好事 小蓝 好极了
Come on, this is a win, Blue. This is a win.
当好事降临
We must celebrate those
- 我们该庆祝一下 - 好吧
- when they come along, just a little bit. - No, okay.
- 你确定这是安全的？- 我确定
- You sure it was safe? - Safe.
你有找到刮胡刀吗？
Is there a razor in that stash of yours?
为何要刮掉？这样看起来比较沉稳
Why? I'll have you know, this is rugged.
- 我觉得有点邋遢 - 是沉稳
- I think it's a bit ragged. - Rugged.
是沉稳
Rugged.
她还好吗？那只小猴子怎么样了？
How is she? How is little monkey?
她已经起床一阵子了
She's been down a while.
或许你该去跟她打声招呼
Maybe you should go say hello.
我不确定她会喜欢我去吵她
I'm not sure she'd like that much.
去睡一下吧
Hey, go and have a lie down.
- 可以吗？- 当然 去吧
- Yeah? - Yeah. Go.
男子汉
Man.
- 你才是 - 配美女
- You are. - Woman.
好女孩 萝西 好乖
Good girl, Rosie. Yes.
（给最忠实的小蓝 结婚纪念日快乐 庆幸我们仍活着 最爱你的安迪上）
太好了
Yes.
好了
Okay.
天啊
Oh!
乖
Hey.
- 妈妈 - 亲爱的 没事了 好了
- Mama. - Hey, darling. Okay, all right.
哦
Ohh!
妈咪
Mommy.
妈咪在哪里？
Where's Mommy then?
她上哪去了？
Where is she?
凯伊？
Kay?
凯伊 你在里面吗？
Kay? Are you in there?
凯伊 让我进去 宝贝
Kay! Come on, let me in, babe.
让我进去
Let me in.
该死 凯伊 怎么...
Shit, Kay, what...
你做了什么？
What have you done?
- 不 别... 别看 - 让我看看
- No, don't... - Let me see.
- 别看 - 继续压着
- No. - Well, keep pressure on it.
- 没事的 没事了 - 妈妈
- Mama. - It's all right. It's okay.
该死
Oh, shit.
（48小时）
来 让我看看
Come on, let me see.
可恶
Oh, fuck.
好了 凯伊 我来... 你做了什么？
Right, Kay, just... Oh, what have you done?
- 我很抱歉 亲爱的 - 没关系 没事的
- I'm sorry, sweetheart. - It's all right. It's okay.
好 继续压着 继续加压
All right, keep that pressure on it. Keep pressure on.
该死
Shit.
- 可以吗？没事吧？- 没事
- Okay. All right? You okay? - Yeah.
可以吗？看着我
All right? Look at me.
- 没事了 - 不会有事的
- It's okay. - It's going to be okay.
（澳洲急救服务）
（发烧 恶心 呕吐 癫痫）
给你
Hey.
- 告诉我 你在想什么？- 我们不能再待在这里了
- So talk to me. What are you thinking? - Well, we can't stay here.
但现在才过一小时 症状至少要三小时...
But it's only been an hour. Symptoms take at least three hours to...
我知道会怎么样 我们可能没有那么多时间
Yeah, I know how it works. We might not have that time.
- 我们不能冒险 - 现在上岸又变成冒险了？
- We can't take the risk. - Oh, so today it's a risk.
因为我现在受了伤 没错 这样就是在冒险
Out there, with this? Yes, it's a risk.
在还不知道要面对什么情况前 我们不能让萝西陷入危险
Let's not put Rosie in danger till we know what we're dealing with.
有数十种生物居住在这河里
There are dozens of things that live and eat in this river.
- 我们不知道是什么东西咬了你 - 那东西有手指 安迪
- We have no idea what bit you. - It had fingers, Andy.
靠
Fuck!
听着 若你被感染了 你只剩48个小时可活
Look, if you are sick, then you've got 48 hours,
那我们可以再做打算
and we'll deal with that.
但若你是错的 你没被感染
But if you're wrong, right, and you're not infected,
照你的失血速度来看 你顶多只能活2-3个小时
then at the rate you're bleeding, you've got two hours, three, tops.
我不会冒这样的风险
That's a risk I'm not gonna take.
我们必须去医院 就像你说过的
We need to get to the hospital, where you said.
有人会替你治疗 我们也能确认你是否被感染
Someone will patch you up and we'll hedge our bets.
要是我真的被感染了呢？
What if we lose?
让我做决定吧
It's gonna be my call.
好吧
Yeah.
来吧
Come on.
别看
Don't look.
来吧 小宝贝
Come on, little darling.
好了
Okay.
乖宝贝 来吧
Oh, good girl. Come here.
你在里头待一下 来吧
Put you in here for a minute. There we go.
快点
Come on.
好样的
Oh, you beauty.
好了
Right.
搞定
Just like that.
- 给我吧 - 谢谢 亲爱的
- Come here. - Thanks, sweetheart.
- 来吧 你待在车里就行了 好吗？- 好
- Come here. I just need you in the car, all right? - Ok.
真不容易
Impossible.
让我来 你去休息吧
I'll get in. Have a fiddle around with it.
好了 我等一下马上就上车
Okay, I'll be two secs.
好了
Right.
好了 宝贝
There you are, poppet.
这是为你挑的新车
There, the new mobile's sorted for you.
妈妈在这里
Mama's here.
乖宝贝
Good girl.
快走
Go!
你还好吗？
How're you feeling?
没什么变化
Like me.
很好
Good.
小猴子 亲爱的 怎么了？
Hey, monkey, what is it, darling?
她需要换尿布
She needs a change.
- 我来吧 - 我来弄就好
- I'll do it. - No, it's fine.
她比较不会闹脾气
She'll make less fuss.
- 是啊 - 来吧 臭屁屁
- 'Course she will. - Come on, stinky trunks.
我们来把你弄干净
Let's get you cleaned up.
来了
There we go.
乖
Hey!
哇
Eww!
萝西小乖乖
Hey, Rosie posie.
凯伊
Kay!
乖 萝西
Hey, Rosie.
凯伊 头靠在我身上
Kay, give me your head.
好了 嘘...
All right. Shh...
嘘
Shh.
- 凯伊 深呼吸 - 停车
- Kay? Just breathe. - Stop the car.
- 看着我 - 停车
- Look at me now. - Stop the car!
- 我们需要冷静下来... - 让我出去
- We need to keep calm... - Let me out now!
天啊 等等
Jesus! Wait!
妈啊
Christ!
凯伊
Kay.
听着 你能否...
Hey, listen. Will you just...
你他妈的别碰我
Fuckin' don't touch me!
安迪 你控制不了这个的
Andy, you can't control this.
你根本无法替我治好这鬼玩意
You don't fucking keep this from me!
我们还要拖多久？直到我攻击你？
How long were you going to play along for? What, until I turn on you?
- 还是她？- 不
- On her? - No.
- 你必须带她走 - 你是什么意思？
- You must take her. - What?
- 你在说什么？要我离开你？小蓝？- 你得带她走
- What are you talking about? Leaving you? - You must take her.
住口 别说了
Stop. Just stop.
够了
Come on.
我在这里 好吗？
I'm here, all right?
不会有事的
It'll be all right.
来吧 我拉你起来
Come on, let's get you up.
我们不去医院
We're not going to the hospital.
我们就快到了
We are so close.
那会让你和萝西离这条河更远
It puts you and Rosie further from the river.
我们现在什么也没有了
There's nothing there for us now.
我们有时间 看到这个了吗？
Yeah there is. Time is there. See this?
这是你剩下的时间 我们要把握每分每秒
That's yours. All of it, every second, and we're gonna make it count.
但若你一直流血 很快就会变成行尸的
But if you bleed out, you'll turn sooner.
要让我做决定 记得吗？
It's my call, remember?
所以我就无权说话？我没选择权？
So I get no say in that? I don't have a choice?
对 亲爱的 你没有权利
No, sweetheart, you don't.
凯伊
Kay.
我不能那么做
I can't do that.
小心 当心这只脚
Watch the leg.
该死
Shit!
凯伊？
Kay?
萝西？
Rosie?
嘿 还好吗？
Hey, how're we doing?
萝西？
Rosie? Rose.
凯伊
Kay.
乖
Hey.
（救她）
小蓝？
Blue?
萝西
Rosie!
该死
Fuck!
可恶
Oh, fuck!
他们要来了
They're coming.
我要你当个乖女儿 乖乖待在这里
I need you to be a very good girl. Stay here.
乖乖在这里等爸爸
Nice and calm for Daddy.
我马上就回来 好吗？萝西 我马上回来
And he'll be right back. Hey, Rosie? Be right back.
哦
Oh.
不 不
No. No.
没事了
Mmm? It's all right.
我知道你喜欢什么
I know what you like.
嗯
Umm.
萝西 是妈咪的味道
Hey, Rosie. It's Mommy.
我闻得到妈咪的味道
I can smell Mommy.
我也闻得到妈咪的味道
I can smell Mommy too.
等等
Hey.
你这家伙
Hey!
你知道自己刚做了什么吗？
Do you know what you just did?
你离我远点 不准过来
You stay away. Stay back.
离我爸远一点
Leave my dad alone!
那玩意显示剩下多少时间？
What's the count left on that business?
嗯...
Uh...
差不多还有46小时
It's 46 hours, give or take.
坐吧
Sit.
让我看看你的手臂
Give us your arm.
这恐怕起不了多大作用
Won't do much, I'm afraid.
但或许能帮把你的伤口藏起来
But it might help you hide it.
最好把伤口都包起来
Best to do that around these parts.
没事了 亲爱的
It's all right, darling.
这是谁？
Who's this then?
萝西
It's Rosie.
- 妈妈 - 小可爱
- Mama. - Little flower.
大家都叫我爱塔
Folks call me Etta.
我叫安迪
Andy.
这地方看起来比地图上小很多
This place looked bigger on the map.
- 我们总是让人失望 - 医院是不是...
- We never fail to disappoint. - The hospital, is it...
- 那称不上医院 只是隔壁的一栋楼 - 好的
That's a generous description. It's the next building over. - Um.
那里没剩什么了 他们几年前削减了我们的资金
There's not much left. They cut our funding years back.
- 你是个老师？- 曾经是
- Are you a teacher? - I was.
你的学生们都上哪去了？
Where are they now, your students?
都走了
Gone.
真遗憾
I'm sorry.
不是死了 是离开了去过传统的生活了
No, not dead. Gone. Living in the old ways.
没什么好遗憾的 他们过得比我们其他人都好
Nothing to be sorry about. They're doing better than the rest of us.
全国各地的暴民都聚集在一起了
Mobs from all over the country coming together.
那些还有在联系的人都感觉到了
They sensed it, those who stayed connected.
这里原本的居民都离开了 回他们自己的国家去
The whole community up and left back to their country.
若你想住在这里的话 这里还有多余的床
There's a spare bed if you want one.
你怎么想 萝西？我们喜欢她吗？
What do you think, Rosie? Do we like her?
我们喜欢她吗？
Do we like her?
我想我们可能喜欢她
I think we might like her.
好了
Okay.
图米
Thoomi!
快回家
Come home!
嘘
Shh.
- 我们现在要拿这些做什么？- 要做矛吗？
- what are we gonna do with this? - Make spears?
有点像妈妈做的意大利面 对吧？
Bit like Mom's spaghetti, eh?
爸
Dad!
以前我们会从动物身上取得这个
Back in the old days, we used to take this from an animal.
智者先生
Mr. Clever Man!
他们在毒害这片土地 你们知道吗？
They're poisoning this land, you know?
这个国家在改变
This country, changing.
这国家病了
It's sick.
我们都会生病
We all get sick.
你也会生病
You get sick too.
（32小时28分钟）
好乖
Yeah.
你好啊 爱塔
Hey, Etta.
你不能那么做 不能放弃希望
You can't do that. You can't lose hope.
这位是威利贝尔
This is Willie Bell.
他是个好人 也是我朋友 他女儿图米是我的学生之一
He's a good man. A friend. His daughter Thoomi was one of mine.
她聪明伶俐
Smart as a whip.
- 跟她爸一个样 - 我见过他们
- Her daddy's shadow. - Yeah, I've seen them.
你回去告诉威利是爱塔要你去的
Well, you just head right back and tell Willie that Etta sent you.
若你想给这个宝宝第二次机会
If you want to give this baby a second chance,
你就该去找他
that's where you go.
好吗？
Yeah?
谢谢你
Thanks.
- 你看到那些火了吗？- 看到了
- Have you seen the fires? - Yeah.
那些狩猎团在清理岛上受感染的人 你必须离远一点
Hunting parties are cleansing the land of the sick ones. You just stay away.
萝西
Hey, Rosie.
再见 亲爱的
Bye bye, darling. Bye bye.
再见
Bye bye.
你自己小心点
Now you take care.
（闪边去 注意 天然气井）
（军事基地）
有人吗？这里是哪里？
Hello, what's here?
给你一些水喝 亲爱的
Let's give you some water, darling.
那是我的
That's mine.
靠
Fuck.
军事基地已经沦陷
Army base is overrun.
还会有更多
There'll be more.
他们在数公里外就能听见那枪声
They would have heard that shot for miles.
最好让那宝宝安静一点
Better keep that baby quiet too.
听着 你把我弄出去 我也会带你离开这里
Listen, how about you get me out of here and then I'll get you out of here?
去哪里？
To where?
一个能让你稍微躲一下的地方
A place you could hole up for a bit.
那小家伙还是要有女人照顾比较好
The little one, be real nice for the wife to have that around.
你最好想快一点 把我拉出来
You better think fast. Tow it off me.
该死
Shit.
- 快点 - 你有钥匙吗？
- Come on. - Got the keys?
你别搞我
Don't you fuck me.
好家伙 拿着这个
Good man. Take this.
来吧 我们走
Come on. Let's go.
这家伙在公路上挥手要搭我的便车
Flagged me down on the highway, this bloke.
他被一些挖土人困住了
Put himself in a spot with some diggers.
你好
Hello.
乖女孩 闭上你的眼睛
Attagirl. Close your eyes.
挺不错的 不 这很美丽
It's nice. No, it's beautiful.
萝伦会带你去安顿一下
Rainey'll get you settled.
我能放她下来吗？
Do you mind if I put her down?
他不曾带人回来的
He doesn't bring people back.
我们很高兴成为他的例外 对吧？
Well, we're very glad he made an exception, aren't we?
谢谢
Thanks.
- 那就是我们在这里的原因 - 因为天然气？
- That's why we're here. - What, the gas?
维克已经规划好回归正轨后的生活
Vic has plans for when things get back to normal.
根本不会有这种事 对吧？
It's not going to happen. Is it?
我觉得应该没那么快
I don't think normal is on the horizon.
（危险 高压天然气管）
你们在天然气公司工作吗？
You worked on the lines?
我在食堂工作
In the canteen.
我负责做菜
I cooked.
这是最重要的工作
Right, well, that's the most important job of all.
男人一定都很爱你
Men must have loved you.
曾经有个人很爱我
One did.
你是我看见的第一个活人
You're the first people I've seen.
第一个还是人的人类
The first people who are still people.
是啊
Yeah.
好了 老兄 我们走吧
All right, mate, let's go.
他们才刚到 维克
They've only just arrived, Vic.
若他习惯了 就会离不开了
Well, if he's in, he's all the way in.
萝伦会照顾她 带她上去 抱抱她
Rainey'll look after her. Take her up there, cuddle her.
她根本不会知道你离开了
Won't even notice you're gone.
我会保护她的安全
I'll keep her safe.
很好
Great.
拜托照顾好她
Please look after her.
好吗？
Okay.
来吧 萝西 这是...
Come on, Rosie. This is...
- 没问题吧？- 妈妈
- You okay? - Mama!
好
Yes.
乖
Hey.
这能让她冷静下来
This calms her down.
好的
Okay.
- 好了... - 回头见
- All right... - See you soon.
是啊
Yeah.
回头见
（反对提炼天然气？滚出去吧 ）
维克
Vic.
这是什么？
What's this?
用过这玩意吗？
Ever used one of these?
没有
No.
往前站 站45度角
Move forward. Stand forty - five.
和目标物呈45度
Forty - five degrees to the target.
然后顶在肩窝...
Now move the stock into your shoulder...
我们要射杀他们？
We're going to shoot them?
没错
Yeah.
反正你也不会想亲他们 对吧？现在把脸颊贴在垫腮板上
You're not gonna kiss 'em, are ya? Now cheek to the cheek plate.
如果目标变得模糊 代表你做对了
If the target's blurry, you're doing it right.
- 是吗？- 懂了吗？
- Yeah? - You got it?
- 我不太确定 可能吧 - 先压着扳机 但别扣下
- Uh, I'm not sure. I think so. - Squeeze the trigger but don't pull it.
- 真的吗？- 没错
- Really? - Yeah.
若你扣了板机 准心就会跑掉 试试看吧
If you pull it, then you throw your sights out. So back up.
现在压着扳机
Now squeeze.
会越来越紧 继续压...
Feel the resistance. Squeeze...
好了
All right.
现在继续射击直到对方倒下 除非全都打倒了... 否则别停下来
Now keep shooting till you drop him... and don't stop till we got 'em all.
快点 我可帮不了你 老兄
Come on, I can't carry you, mate.
我以为我们是为了天然气而来
I thought we were here for gas.
- 这叫额外的收入 - 那她怎么办？
- Call it a side earner. - What's that got to do with her?
没有鱼饵 鱼就上不了钩
Can't catch a fish without bait.
当国家回到正轨 大家就会开始有物欲
When this country gets back on track, people are gonna want things.
能控制市场 能源 天然气
Whoever controls the market, power, gas...
拥有闪亮亮的东西的... 人就能享受安乐的生活
all the shiny shit... will be sitting pretty.
打铁要趁热嘛
I'm just making hay while the sun shines.
你想太多了 维克
The sun's not shining, Vic.
什么对你来说才重要？
What's it worth to ya?
一个让你和孩子安全的地方？
A safe place for you and your kid?
你只需要担心自己的女儿就好
Only girl you need to be worried about is your own.
把这个装满
Fill it up.
没事的
Hey, it's okay.
别怕 只是天然气快没了
No, just low on gas, that's all.
天然气快没了而已
Just low on gas.
嘘
Shh.
萝西
Hey, Rosie.
我告诉过你
I told you mob.
那些天然气井是我的 里面的东西也是我的
The wells are mine along with what's in 'em.
若敢跟我斗
Fuck with me...
我就绝不会放过你
and I'll fuck with you.
你在里面看起来挺孤单的
You look lonely in there.
放点音乐给你召几个朋友过来吧
See if we can drum you up some company.
∮ Full of pain and misery ∮
∮ A crazy thing ∮
∮ Anyone out there cares about you ∮
∮ Our loves are deep ∮
∮ Like I do Trust me ∮
∮ With your love tonight ∮
∮ Trust me It will be all right ∮
∮ I'm in Heaven when he's in my hand... ∮
她在睡觉
She's sleeping.
你今天做得不错
You did well today.
或许我们可以考虑让你住下来
Maybe we can talk about you staying on permanent.
我帮她洗过澡了
I cleaned her up.
∮ 一闪一闪亮晶晶 ∮
∮ Twinkle, twinkle, little star ∮
喔
Oop.
∮ 满天都是小星星 ∮
∮ How I wonder what you are ∮
好了 你乖乖睡吧
Come on. You're all right. Come on.
天啊
Oh.
嘿 萝西
Hey, Rosie.
我爱你
I love you.
快动手啊 孬种
Come on, you fucker.
快动手 孬种
拜托你别那么做
Please don't.
萝伦
Lorraine.
你不该来这里的
You shouldn't be here.
我知道你想做什么 我也知道原因
I know what you're doing, and I know why.
拜托你 帮我照顾她
Please, just look after her for me.
我会的
I will.
但我在这里无法保护她
But not here.
- 萝伦 这里最安全了 - 在他身边就不安全
- Lorraine, this is as safe as it gets. - Not from him.
- 你剩几小时？- 大概20小时
- What's your count? - It's around 20.
- 带我们去别的地方 - 他虽然不完美 但这里很安全
- Take us somewhere else. - He is not perfect, but here it's secure.
- 你先生... - 他不是我先生
- Your husband... - He's not my husband.
那家伙眼睁睁看着我先生和其他人死在天然气厂
That man left my husband to die at the gas plant with everyone else.
他为了让自己活命 把他们锁在里面
Locked them in to save his own skin.
我绝对会比他更能保护这小女孩
I could protect this little girl more than he ever will.
但在这里没办法
But not here.
河边有一户人家 但我不确定他们是否活着
There is a family by the river. I don't know if they're still alive.
- 我不确定我们能否及时赶到 - 这里看起来挺舒适的
- I don't know if we can make it in time. - This looks cozy.
要是我不知道的话 我还以为你想拐走我的女人 安迪
If I didn't know better, I'd think you were trying to steal my girl, Andy.
你别想太多了
You do know better.
萝西
Rosie!
维克
Vic!
快让我出去 混蛋 我不会伤害你的
Come on, let me out, you fuck! I'm not going to hurt you.
我不会伤害你的 好吗？
I'm not going to hurt you, okay?
好 你来一下 我得研究这个锁
Okay, come with me. I need to have a look at this.
天啊 听着 我不会伤害你 我保证
God, look, I'm not going to hurt you, I promise you.
当我我看见你... 我昨天看见你的时候
When I saw you... when I saw you yesterday...
我很抱歉 你可以对我生气 我不介意
I'm sorry about that. You can be mad at me.
但若你想出去 只能靠我了 我们一起合作吧
If you want out, I'm your ticket. Let's play ball.
你想去找你的朋友？
Do you want to see your friend?
他不是我的朋友 我只是要把女儿抱回来
He's not my friend. I just want my daughter back.
- 我也想要某个东西 - 你要什么？
- I want something too. - What do you want?
他那把能打开智者先生笼子的钥匙
His keys to the Clever Man's cage.
不管你要什么都可以
Whatever that is, you can have 'em.
- 他们要来了 - 什么？
- They're coming. - Huh?
那些鬼 他们闻到味道了
The ghosts. They smell it.
再加把劲
Come on.
该死
Shit.
等这栅栏被拉起 你就马上出来
When this lifts up, you gotta slide out straight away.
很好 就是这样
Come on. That's it.
快 就是现在 我们走
Come on! That's it! Let's go!
快走
Go!
来 萝伦 我来抱她吧
Here, Lorraine, give her to me.
该死的小偷
Fucking thief!
给我回来
Get back here!
- 安迪 - 不
- Andy! - No!
维克 不要
Vic, no!
萝伦
Rainey!
他不见了 来吧 我们走吧
He's gone. Come on, let's go.
等等
Wait.
我闻到你的臭味了 你这小人
I can smell your rot, you weasly cunt!
- 你带走不属于你的东西 - 该死
- What you took didn't belong to you! - Shit.
把那他妈的黑婊子还给我
You give me back the fucking black bitch!
她是我的
She's mine!
若你把她还给我 或许我能放你女儿一马
If you give her to me, then maybe there'll be a happy ending for your kid!
但如果你让我找到你们
But if I have to fucking come looking,
你就死定了 而且她们会更惨
then it'll be bad for you and worse for them.
嘘
Shh.
或许我在这等个两天就行了吧？
Maybe I'll just wait a couple of days, huh?
直到你已经不是你自己
Until you're not you anymore.
我就可以眼睁睁...
And I'll just watch...
看着你把她们吃了
while you eat their fucking faces off.
好孩子
Good girl.
图米 我得回到河边 你能带我去吗？
Thoomi, I need to get back to the river. Can you show me the way?
我必须要找到智者先生
I've gotta find the Clever Man.
听着 我没时间... 智者先生到底是什么？
Oh, look, I don't have time for... What is a Clever Man, anyway?
是一个聪明的人还是什么？
Is he just a smart guy, or what?
他是一个魔法师
He's a magic man.
若你生病了 他能给你良药
If you're sick, he can give you good medicine.
若有人偷走了你的灵魂 他可以帮你要回来
And if someone steals your spirit away, he can put it back again.
嘿 你觉得你爸变成那样是因为他失去了灵魂？
Hey, you think your dad is acting the way he is because he lost his soul?
图米 有很多人都像你爸那样走路
There are lots of people walking around like your dad.
- 我爸跟其他人不一样 - 不 我并不认同
- My dad's different. - I don't think that's true.
我跟你爸都无药可救了
There's no fixing what your father and I have.
有很多聪明的人都试过了
Lots of other smart guys have tried.
你要去哪里？
Where are you going?
我要去看个东西
I've gotta check something.
看什么？
Check what?
图米 你要看什么？
Thoomi, check what?
我的老天
For fuck's sake.
（威利）
天啊 图米
Jesus, Thoomi.
快住手
Hey, stop!
走开
Go away!
这是缅怀仪式 你只是个愚蠢的“嘎把”
This is sorry business. You're just a stupid gubba.
你什么都不懂
You don't know anything.
那是我爸
That's my dad.
我们会把死者埋在树中 鬼魂就无法唤醒他们
We get buried in the trees so the ghosts can't wake us.
他的灵魂仍不在他身上
His spirit's still loose.
这都是我的错
It's my fault.
我浪费太多时间了
I took too long.
不 不是你的错
No you didn't.
你没有浪费太多时间 这不是你的错
No you didn't. This isn't your fault.
我把他绑在这里 好让我能把智者先生带来
I tied him here till I could bring the Clever Man back.
族人不该找到他的
They weren't supposed to find him.
他们认为自己在做正确的事
They thought they were doing the right thing.
他们做得也没错
They did.
他已不再是你爸了
That wasn't your dad anymore.
很遗憾 但他已经变了
I'm sorry, but it wasn't.
我应该把智者先生带来 而不是带你来
I should have been here, with him, not you.
图米 我得走了 对不起
Thoomi, I have to go. I'm sorry.
我觉得萝西希望你跟我们一起走
I think Rosie would like it if you came with us.
你跟我们一起走的话 我会比较开心
I'd be happier if you did.
我根本不在乎你和你的女儿
I don't care about you or your baby.
我觉得你不是真心说这话的
I don't think you mean that.
她不会有事的
She'll be okay.
她不会有事的 该死
She'll be okay. Shit.
该死
Shit.
（9小时2分钟）
萝西？
Rosie?
河往这边走
River's this way.
你弄那些树叶干什么？
What's with the leaves?
这样可以隐藏我的脚印
They hide my footprints.
你怕谁看到？那些鬼吗？
From who? The ghosts?
不 我妈
No, my mom.
有人吗？
Hello?
饿吗？
Hungry?
太好了
Yes.
找到了
Bingo.
可能会有点刺痛
This might sting a little bit.
伤口在哪边？
Where is it?
这里吗？准备好了吗？
There? Ready?
你为什么要那么做？
Why'd you do that?
那是传统的生活
It's from the old ways.
但已经不再是我们的传统了
But not our ways anymore.
为什么？
Then why?
因为很痛
'Cause it hurts.
当这里的伤口愈合 或许心里的伤口也会愈合
When this hurt heals, maybe this hurt heals too.
住这里的人去哪里了？
Where did all the people go?
应该没走远
Not far.
食物还很新鲜
The food's still fresh.
你为什么要找他们？
Why do you want 'em?
因为我想请他们帮忙
'Cause I want to ask them a favor.
你女儿吗？他们会让她留下吗？
About bub? Are they gonna keep her?
我们应该要想想你该怎么办
We should think about what we're gonna do with you.
或许他们不会回来了
Maybe they won't come back.
我觉得他们应该会
I think they will.
要是他们没回来呢？
What if they don't?
那你就是我最后的希望了
Then you're all I've got.
你好
Hello?
露营车可以给你
The caravan's yours.
只要你能发动 车子也给你
Car too, if you can start it.
我需要的不是车子
It's not the car I need.
听着
Look.
我有六发子弹 好吗？
I've got six, okay?
若你变成行尸 最后两颗留给你
The last two are yours, if you go that way.
- 拜托你别那么做 - 不 我不能丢下他们
- Please, don't do that. - I can't leave them.
我会说到做到 所以...
I said I wouldn't and I won't, so...
冷静点
Hey.
你看 爸爸 那个人抱着宝宝
Look, Daddy, that man has a baby!
是啊
Yes, he does.
我们跟宝宝说再见 好吗？
Should we say goodbye to the baby?
好
Yeah.
他们要走了
They're leaving now.
再见 宝宝
Bye bye, baby!
老兄
Hey, mate.
你就用那两颗子弹吧
Just take the two.
就算是为了她好
For her sake.
我的海盗们在哪里？
Where's my pirate, ey?
我们要去寻找宝藏了吗？
We gonna come and find this treasure?
走吧
Hey? Come on.
爸
Dad.
爸爸
Daddy.
来抱抱 萝西
Come here, Rosie.
你好啊 图米
Hey, Thoomi.
你好 爸
Hey.
你好啊
你脚下的树叶呢？
What's happened to your leaves?
我想回家了
I wanna go home now.
真的吗？
Really?
你想见见我家人吗？
You want my people?
好啊
Yeah.
我想
Yeah, I do.
图米 若我没能爬到山上 你...
Thoomi, if I don't make it to the hills, you...
- 不需要爬山 你看到了吗？- 什么？
- You don't have to. See? - Hmm?
他们就在不远处
They're close.
阿特拉
Atla.
意思是火
Fire.
阿特拉 跟我说“阿特拉”
Atla. Say atla.
好
Okay.
- 这是什么？- 让那些鬼没办法跟着我们
- What's that? - Makes it so the ghosts can't track us.
真的吗？
Really?
- 我最好也擦一点 - 不需要
- I'd better put some on. - You don't need any.
你的味道已经跟那些鬼一样了
You smell like them already.
里面好可怕
Proper creepy in there.
外面也很可怕
Proper creepy here by to.
他们要冬眠 所以需要在黑暗的地方
They're hibernating. They need the dark.
维克
Vic!
他妈的混蛋
You fuck!
给我出来
Get the fuck outta there.
出来
Get out!
不 住手
Don't! Stop!
嘘
Shh.
图米 你还好吗？
Thoomi! You all right?
天啊 萝西呢？
Oh, God. Where's Rosie?
萝西在哪里？
Where's Rosie?
没事的
It's all right.
萝西
Rosie.
嘘
Shh.
把她给我 维克
Give her to me, Vic.
快点 老兄
Come on, mate.
我们俩都死定了
We're both fucked.
维克 我对上帝发誓
Vic, I swear to Christ.
若你敢伤害她
If you hurt her...
你拿走我的东西 现在我也要拿走你的东西
You took mine, now, I take yours.
萝伦不是你的 维克
Lorraine wasn't yours though, Vic.
维克 不要...
Vic, don't...
你最好别这样做
Don't you dare.
听我说 维克
Listen to me, Vic.
够了
It's done.
好了 宝贝
All right. All right, darling.
没事了 宝贝
All right, darling.
图米？
Thoomi?
我知道你受伤了 宝贝
I know you're hurt, darling.
但你不能倒下
Stay with me.
图米
Thoomi.
图米 拜托你了
Thoomi, please.
你若倒下 我们就无法前进了 知道吗？
We can't go any further if you don't walk, okay?
你了解吗？
Do you understand me?
图米 清醒点 亲爱的
Thoomi, wake up. Wake up, darling.
你能帮我吗？
Are you gonna help me?
我们互相帮忙 好吗？
Let's help each other, yeah?
- 好 - 好女孩
- Yeah. - Good girl.
教我说些你们的族语吧 “太阳”怎么说？
Teach me some of those words, mate. Teach me how to say, "sun".
什么？
Hmm?
不然教我“天空”怎么说
Teach me how to say "sky", then.
老天 随便教我点什么吧
Christ, teach me something.
教我你们是怎么说“爸爸”的 你们都怎么说？
Teach me how to say "daddy". How do you say that?
- 瓦毗 - “瓦毗” 很好
- Vapi. - Vapi. Great.
那“女儿”怎么说？
How do you say "daughter"?
- 瓦普露 - 好的
- Vapalu. - Yeah!
你们怎么说... 你之前叫我什么来着？
How do you say... What's that word you called me?
“嘎把” 那是什么意思？
Gubba. What was that? What does that mean?
- 白人 - 白...
- White fella. - White fella.
白人
White fella.
那你们怎么说“朋友”？
Well, how do you say "friend"?
- 米塔 - “米塔”
- Mita. - Mita.
好 “米塔”
Yeah, mita.
我比较喜欢这个词
I prefer that one.
停
Stop.
过来
Come here.
好 我要解开
Okay. Let go.
快来帮我一下
Come. Help me.
帮我一下
Help me.
抱着她
Hold onto her.
该死
Oh, shit.
你要跟紧我 不然他们会闻到我们
Stay close or they'll smell us.
你看
See?
我脸上的颜料越来越淡
My paint's coming off.
抱走她
Take it.
帮我放下来
Take it away.
好
Okay.
你别想太多
Now don't worry about this.
就把这个当作你妈妈做的意大利面 好吗？
You just treat this like it's mom's spaghetti, okay?
好了
All right.
你要替我照顾她 好吗？因为我要离开了
Look after her for me, okay? 'Cause I'm going now.
“米塔” 帮我照顾好她 好吗？
Look after her. Will you do that for me, mita?
- 我会的 - 好
- I will. - All right, mate.
- 我答应你 - 谢谢你
- I promise. - Thank you.
宝贝
Hey.
萝西 你会得到妥善的照顾
Hey, Rosie, you're in good hands.
别担心 她会照顾好你的
You're in good hands. She's gonna look after you, mate.
我爱你
I love you.
爱你
Love you.
图米 就是现在
Thoomi. Thoomi, now.
现在
Now.
（谢谢）